# DIANA ZULUAGA



## **PROFILE**

Environmental engineer with 3+ years of experience in data science applied to climate research and energy industry. Especially interested in automation, data processing and predictive modelling. Passionate about learning new things and collaborating with people. Cooking, hiking and mountain biking enthusiast.

# **SKILLS**

Python: pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn

Data visualization: plotly, matplotlib, seaborn, folium

Statistics Data analysis Geospatial analysis

Machine learning | Time series | SQL | Docker

### **EXPERIENCE**

### **RESEARCHER**

### Ministry of Science

🛗 Sep 2020 - Ago 2022

- Medellín, Colombia
- Delivered a diagnosis of the availability and variability of solar power resource in Colombia as part of Government initiative to promote renewable energy projects in the country.

#### MARKET EXCHANGES ANALYST

#### XM Compañía Expertos en Mercados S.A. E.S.P.

- Automated settlement and billing of energy market transactions for Colombia's grid operator to optimize the process and meet regulatory deadlines.
- Implemented changes in the settlement and billing of energy market transactions based on regulatory changes.

#### JUNIOR RESEARCHER

#### **EIA University**

m Jan 2019 - Jun 2019

- Medellín, Colombia
- Characterized spatial and temporal variability of solar radiation in Colombia.

### INTERN ENGINEER

#### ISAGEN S.A. E.S.P.

# Jan 2018 - Jul 2018

- Automated long-term hydrological flow projections of rivers that serve as affluents of Colombia's water reservoirs, to optimize operation of hydraulic power plants.

# **LANGUAGES**

English C1 Spanish Native

# **EDUCATION**

M.Eng. in Water Resources Engineering

### **National University of Colombia**

**2020 - 2022** 

Medellin, Colombia

B.Eng. in Environmental Engineering **EIA University** 

**2014 - 2018** 

Medellin, Colombia

## **CERTIFICATES**

Data Scientist - Data Science For All (DS4A)

Correlation One - Ministry of IT

## Sep 2020 - Nov 2020

# **PROJECTS**

- Predicting high-tension transmission line failures due to atmospheric discharges (Final Project, Data Science for All DS4A, Colombia).
- Spatio-temporal variability of solar resource in Colombia (Master's Thesis, National University of Colombia, Medellin, Colombia).
- Assessment of interpolation techniques for solar radiation in Colombia (Bachelor's Degree Final Project, EIA University, Medellin, Colombia).

# **REFERENCES**

### Héctor Gómez Marín

- @ Market Exchanges Specialist in XM S.A. E.S.P.

### Santiago Ortega Arango

- @ Director I+D+i in Emergente Energía Sostenible S.A.S.